### RESUME: COLONEL RAJENDRA SINGH BHANDARI (VETERAN)



Senior professional who is widely travelled, has an impressive career and impeccable record. Has over four decades of experience in personnel and material management, training, recruitment, administration, security and disaster management. Passionately pursues long term vision of the organization with tireless commitment in getting things done innovatively leading to desired transformation.

Date of Birth: February 20, 1952.

#### **Educational Qualification:**

- (a) Graduate of the National Defence Academy (Pune) and the Indian Military Academy (Dehradun).
- (b) A prestigious and coveted Long Gunnery Staff Course at School of Artillery Deolali, where in, Pune University now awards M Sc Tech (Weapon System) i.e. Specialization in Armament.
- (c) A senior level executive management (Senior Command) course at Army War College Mhow.
- (d) Management Development Programme on Leadership for Professional Excellence for Senior Officers at MDI Gurgaon.

## **Professional Experience:**

- (a) **Indian Army.** While in the Indian Army (Regiment of Artillery) from Dec 1972 to Feb 2006 held several crucial positions across the country spanning thirty three years of distinguished service. Assignments as a Colonel are given below with details attached as **Appendix:** 
  - (i) <u>Administrative Assignment</u>. Administrative Commandant Jaipur Military Station from Mar 2004 to Feb 2006.
  - (ii) <u>Senior Staff Officer</u>. Colonel General Staff (SD & WE/EM) in Corps HQs including Operation Parakram from Jan 2002 to Feb 2004.
  - (iii) <u>Talent Acquisition & Recruitment</u>. Director Recruitment at Army Recruitment Office Almora from Nov 1999 to Dec 2001.
  - (iv) <u>Senior Management</u>. Deputy Brigade Commander of an Artillery Brigade in J & K on LoC including Op Vijay from Apr 1997 to Oct 1999.
  - (v) <u>Training & Development</u>. Regimental Commander at Artillery Training Centre Nasik from Jul 1994 to Mar 1997.
  - (vi) <u>CEO</u>. Commanding Officer of a Combat Unit (Medium Regiment) in Western/ Eastern Sector (Arunachal Pradesh) with active CI operations (Op Rhino) in Assam from May 1992 to Jun 1994.
- (b) <u>Securities and Exchange Board of India(SEBI)</u>. General Manager (Protocol & Security) at Mumbai from Sep 2006 to Feb 2014.

### **Achievements and Recognitions:**

- (a) At SEBI started up Protocol & Security Division. Therein architected very effective protocol, security and firefighting architecture in terms of infrastructure, manpower, equipment, systems and procedures at the Head Office, four Regional Offices, sixteen Local Offices and residential areas. The mailing, visitor and disaster management procedures were streamlined to make these responsive and accountable. Inducted ex- servicemen as Administrative and Technical Support Staff in October 2008 at a great personal risk against external difficulties, which is the main stay of SEBI Head Office security and visitor management architecture.
- (b) Pioneered induction of Maharashtra Security Force (MSF) at SEBI Head Office against external odds in May 2013.
- (c) In a huge initiative founded Area Security Advisory Panel (ASAP) in 2007, a collaborative forum wherein Security Chiefs of various institutes of Bandra Kurla Complex (BKC) were brought on one platform for interaction with Govt law enforcement and disaster agencies and mutual support in security/disaster management. The ASAP's work has placed security professionals squarely on the Mumbai map. The tangible recommendations made by ASAP have found favour with the Govt bodies. Authored Emergency Response Tips and distributed 40000 copies in public.
- (d) Due to selfless community services in the field of development, beautification and security was elected as the Vice Chairman of the Association of Members of G Block, BKC and Member of the MMRDA Core Group (Improvement of Infrastructure in BKC).
- (e) Fellowship of International Institute of Security and Safety Management (IISSM), New Delhi.
- (f) Received the "Best Security Professional 2012" award from the IISSM, New Delhi in October 2012.
- (g) Case study on Corporate Collaborative Security Initiative in BKC in form of Area Security Advisory Panel (ASAP) was adjudged as the Best Case Study (Runners up) from the IISSM, New Delhi in December 2009.
- (h) Case study on Transforming Ex- servicemen from Security Guards to Administrative & Technical Support Staff at SEBI Mumbai was adjudged as the Best Case Study by the IISSM, New Delhi October 2012.
- (i) As Commanding Officer, turned a sick unit (not fit for war) into a gallant Artillery Regiment, which later fired over 23,000 rounds in Op Vijay and won the battle honour 'KARGIL'.
- (j) Successfully executed crisis and disaster management (CI ops- Op Rhino) in Johrat and Golaghat Districts of Assam for about two years during peak insurgency. This involved direct leading of men under adverse conditions and motivated them to the extent of self sacrifice in face of the insurgents.
- (k) Attended numerous prestigious security and disaster related professional seminars, conferences and exhibitions, including as guest speaker.

## **Present Address:**

Flat No 203, Krishna Kunj, Gen A K Vaidya Marg, Gokuldham, Goregaon (East), Mumbai-400063

Email: rsbcol64@gmail.com & Tele: 022-28427605 / 9833175631

Family Details: Wife, son, daughter and daughter- in- law.

# ASSIGNMENTS AS A COLONEL IN THE INDIAN ARMY

- 1. Administrative Commandant Jaipur Military Station. Executed infrastructural development of the region involving military areas in the six Northern districts of Rajasthan. Other functions included general management, security, land management, liaison with local/State civil authorities; provisioning and control of equipment/stores including logistics build up in operations. Custody/maintenance of defence estates, classification/ allotment of residential accommodation to officers and housing of troops in the station, control of station transport, supplies, maintenance of health and distribution / despatch of ordnance stores were other functions. Started up Ex-servicemen Contributory Health Scheme (ECHS) Polyclinics and operationally and financially managed these. Played a major role in beautification of the Military Station and housing of the HQ South Western Command including its personnel during its raising in 2005.
- **2.** Colonel General Staff (Staff Duties & Weapons and Equipment/Equipment Management) at Corps HOs. Coordinated and promulgated of General Staff (GS) policy of all Arms and Services. Implemented GS movement policy, mobilization of units, location policy, general policy on tours and visits, convening and coordinating important conferences, staff duties procedures, policy on telephone and other static communication, including during Op Parakram. In addition formulated and reviewed organizational structure of formations / units and administered civilian personnel Weapons/equipment management included inventory management, accounting, releases, procurement, trials, preservation and monitoring of serviceability state to ensure high state of operational preparedness.
- 3. <u>Director Recruitment at Army Recruitment Office Almora</u>. The area of recruitment included entire state of UP and Uttarakhand. The responsibility encompassed recruiting publicity, motivation for recruitment, maintenance of close liaison with civil administration/educational institutions/media, organizing recruitment rallies, selection and enrollment. Above all was responsible for conducting motivational seminars for entry in to officer cadre in the Army. In addition researched and compiled publications for aspiring candidates for recruitment of officers and other ranks.
- **4.** <u>Deputy Brigade Commander of Artillery Brigade.</u> Assisted in strategic and operational planning of Artillery Brigade on the LoC including Op Vijay. Other functions included career development, performance appraisal and hygiene factors of more than 3000 troops and their families. Planned and coordinated administrative support for units spread over a large geographical area to include material management, inventory control, accounting, budget projections and ammunition expenditure.
- **5.** Regimental Commander at Artillery Training Centre Nasik. Trained over 2000 young men and converted them into trained soldiers and craftsmen. Planned and coordinated their further career development. Oversaw logistics functions covering a wide spectrum of activities such as housing, welfare activities, sports, funds and grants to the tune of several crores. Organised Reunion of the Regiment of Artillery spread over five days, with participation by over 1500 delegates including serving and retired military dignitaries.
- **6.** Commanding Officer of Combat Unit (Medium Regiment). Functions encompassed personnel management, general administration, materal management worth several crores, financial management and HRD. It required to conceptualize and overseeing implementations of policies, motivation, morale building, logistics and welfare of about 700 personnel at various levels. Ensured optimum utilization and maintenance of equipment worth several crores for maximum efficiency. Planning and assessment of training needs, performance appraisal and development of career in respect of personnel under command fell in the ambit.